天哪
Dear me,
我从来没看过这么多张拉长的脸聚在一起
I've never seen so many long faces.
出席葬礼的传统就是要表现出悲哀
It is customary to be sad at a funeral.
是啊，共和国已经腐朽老化
Well, the Republic is old and infirm.
在这种时候，死亡反而是种解脱
Death can be a merciful release in such cases.
这不是你的本意
You do not mean that.
你不是这么想的
You don't believe that.
你们不应该开有关独裁的玩笑
You of all people shouldn't lay jokes
我可是认真的
about tyranny.  Oh, I am deadly serious.
归顺于恺撒
It is in all our interests
既符合我们的利益
to be reconciled with Caesar now,
也是为了罗马好
for the good of Rome.
真正的为罗马好
The good of Rome indeed.
一旦这场闹剧结束
As soon as this... farce is done,
我就隐退到乡下
I shall retire to the country
看着这座城市慢慢的恢复过来
and wait for the city to come to its senses.
这是保留尊严的唯一办法了
It is the only honorable thing to do.
得了，我的朋友
My dear friend,
我们早就没有尊严
we have no honor.
如果我们还有尊严
If we had honor, we would be
早就和卡托，西比乌一起死了
with Cato and Scipio in the afterlife.
首先，元老院将听取马库斯·图里亚斯·西赛罗的发言
First, Senate will hear Marcus Tullius Cicero.
在这个荣耀的凯旋庆典日之前
On this eve of his most glorious triumph,
我推举盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
I move that Gaius Julius Caesar
未来十年内
be made lmperator
作为拥有无上权力的
and granted absolute power over Rome
罗马元首
for a period of 10 years.
正如大家所知道的
As some of you know,
恺撒和我也有过意见不合的时候
Caesar and I have had our disagreements.
尽管如此
However that may be,
他还是在
he has shown himself
胜利之后体现了他的明智和大度
to be as wise and merciful in victory
正如他在战场上无往不胜一般
as he was invincible in battle.
让这场内部的矛盾
Let this be an end
早日结束吧
to division and civil strife.
我将向恺撒献出我的忠诚
I willingly pledge my loyalty to him,
也希望所有人都如此
and I urge you all to do the same.
我由衷的赞成
I heartily commend
马库斯·图里亚斯·西赛罗
the motion proposed
提出的建议
by Marcus Tullius Cicero.
提议得到全票通过
The motion is carried unanimously.
在座的很多人
Many of you here today
都曾经和我对立
fought against me.
很多人希望看到我死
Many of you wished me dead.
也许很多现在仍然如此
Many of you perhaps still do.
但我并不介意
But I hold no grudges
也不打算报复
and seek no revenge.
我只要求你们
I demand only this--
和我站在一起
that you join with me
建立一个新的罗马
in building a new Rome,
一个新的罗马
a Rome that offers
能让他所有的公民们都
justice, peace and land
生活在公平，和平和富饶的土地上
to all its citizens,
而不只是那些特权阶级
not just the privileged few.
帮助我完成这项使命
Support me in this task,
过去的分歧都既往不咎
and old divisions will be forgotten.
如果你反对我…
Oppose me...
罗马将不会给你第二次机会
and Rome will not forgive you a second time.
元老们…
Senators...
战争已经结束
the war is over.
女主人
Domina.
Mmm?
朱莉娅·阿提娅来了
Atia of the Julii is here.
阿提娅？
Atia?
是的，已经到了
Here, now.
她想见见你
She wishes to see you.
阿提娅…
Atia...
在我的房子里？
in my house?
亲爱的阿提娅
My dear Atia.
见到你实在太好了
How lovely to see you.
亲爱的
Bona dea.
我可怜的朋友
My poor friend.
他们都对你做了些什么？
What have they done to you?
你太客气了
You're so sweet.
坐下吧
Come sit down.
抱歉我没有早点来看你
I'm very sorry I haven't visited sooner,
说实话，我是因为心情太差而没早来见你的
but to be honest, I was far too upset to face seeing you.
一个贵妇被扒光了衣服在大街上被羞辱
The very idea, it's- it's too sinister.
这个画面一直在我脑海中挥之不去，实在是太邪恶了
A noblewoman stripped naked and beaten on the streets--
太可怕了，太可怕了
horrible. Horrible.
告诉我，你现在怎么样了？
Tell me truly, how are you now?
我恢复的很好
I'm recovering very well.
他们找到动手的人了吗？
Have they found the culprits yet?
还没有，不过因果报应总有时
They have not, but justice will find them eventually.
我相信这点
I'm quite sure of that.
要来点柠檬水么？
Would you have some lemon water?
好的
That would be lovely.
布鲁图斯还好吧？ 他很好
Brutus is well, I hope.  He is.
他向我的叔叔屈服实在是太明智了
It's so wise of him to choose submission to my dear uncle.
我很怕他会为了所谓的勇猛
I was very afraid he might try
干出一些鲁莽的事情来
some foolish act of bravery.
男人总是会为了尊严干点蠢事
Men are so silly about their honor. No?
我来是想问你
I've come to ask you
你愿意在凯旋庆典时和我坐在一起吗？
if you will sit with me at the triumph.
很多吹嘘拍马之徒都在我身边
Even though I'm being besieged by sycophants
乞求我给他们一个位子，但我不这么想
asking for space, I thought, "No,
我第一想到的人
if someone were to have first choice,
就是我的好朋友赛维莉娅
it should be my dear friend Servilia
她经历了这么多的痛苦
who's been through so much pain."
你想的真是周到…
That is very thoughtful of you...
但我认为我不够资格
but I think I shall not be well enough.
真遗憾…
Well, that's a pity.
你真的这么想吗？ 是的
Are you sure?  I am.
好吧，如果你回心转意的话… 我会告诉你的
Well, if you change your mind-  I will let you know.
有人告诉我奥克塔维娅离开了城里
People tell me that Octavia's left the city,
但没人知道她去了哪
but no one knows where.
希望别出什么事了
I hope there's nothing amiss.
别担心
Not at all.
她呆在我表兄在帕斯图的一幢别墅里
She's staying at my cousin's villa in Paestum,
和一个她遇到的愚蠢的年轻诗人在一起呆着
mooning over some young fool of a poet she's met there.
凯旋庆典之时她就会回来
She'll be back in time for the triumph.
弟弟
Brother.
你来这里干什么？
What are you doing here?
我是来带你回家的
I've come to take you home.
这里就是我的家  这里？
This is my home.  This? This is not your home.
这不是你的家
I'm happy here.
我在这很愉快
我可不相信
I don't believe you.
无论如何，和家人在一起的地方才是你的家
In any case, your place is with your family.
离开家庭是愚蠢的
Bad enough to run away,
和这些人一起生活？
but to these people? This isn't the healthy way of life.
这样的生活方式是不健康的
你认为我们家很健康吗？
You call our family healthy?
从大地上都能嗅出我们家的腐败
Our corruption stinks in the nostrils of Mother Earth.
这都是那些愚蠢祭司的说法
This is your foreign priests talking.
他们都是骗子，只是想要你的钱
They are frauds. They only want your money.
祭司在这里不是别的，都是仆人而已
Priests are nobody. They are just servants here.
这是圣母的领地
This is the Great Mother's house.
圣母对我没有他求
The Great Mother wants nothing from me.
我在她眼中只是渺小的虫子罢了  你可不是什么虫子
I'm a worm in her sight.  You are not a worm.
你是朱利亚家的女儿
You are a daughter of the Julii.
你变成这样实在让人看的心疼
It looks very ill, you running away like this.
如果让大众知道的话
Reflects badly on the whole family
会给我们家造成极大的不良影响
if it were known publicly.
我还以为你是期盼我回去
For a moment I thought you wanted me back
是因为你很想我  别傻了
because you missed me.  Don't be silly.
我们都很想你
We've missed you terribly.
母亲也很想你
Your mother has missed you.
我相信仆人和那些小动物们也期盼着你回去
I believe even the servants and animals
还有你？
have missed you.  And you?
当然还有我
And I.
我很想你
I've missed you.
我不能回去
I can't go back.
已发生的事情是无法挽回的了
What's done is done.
我原谅你了，还有母亲也原谅你
I forgive you. Your mother forgives you.
你原谅我？
You forgive me?
母亲原谅我？
Mother forgives me?
如果我并不原谅你们呢？
What if I don't forgive?
不论你认为她做了什么
Whatever you think she may have done,
想一下这都是她出于对你的爱
consider the possibility she did it out of love for you.
我永远不会原谅她
I'll never forgive her.
就算是那样，你的宽恕也无关紧要
Be that as it may, your forgiveness is irrelevant.
你必须回家
You must come home.
对不起
I'm sorry,
我不回去
I will not.
我不想使用武力
I don't want to use force.
祭司们会保护我的
The priests will protect me.
他们不会的
They won't.
我已经收买了他们
I've bought them.
很便宜的价格
Quite cheaply.
求你了
I beg you,
让我留在这里吧
Iet me stay here.
你都干了些什么？
What have you done?
艾文泰的居民们
Fellow citizens of the Aventine!
居民们
Fellow citizens!
艾文泰的居民们
Fellow citizens of the Aventine!
我的名字是卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
My name is Lucius vorenus,
斯特拉提纳族人，第13军团的退伍军人
tribe of Stellatina, veteran of the 1 3th Legion.
你们中的某些人也许认识我
Some of you may know me.
我给你们带来了好消息
I bring you good news.
恺撒已经结束了贵族们的苛政
Caesar has put an end to patrician tyranny,
他确定民众们的声音
and will ensure that the common people
将会再次得到尊重  滚回高卢去吧
be heard once more.  Go back to Gaul, ginger knob.
生姜头
我不会否认，我的朋友我的外表看起来的确是高卢人
I'll not deny it, friend, I have a Gallic look about me,
但我确实是个罗马人
but I'm as solid Roman as you are.
我为罗马抛头颅撒热血
I've shed blood for Rome.
我的父亲也为罗马浴血奋战
My father shed blood for Rome,
我的祖父和曾祖父同样如此
as did his father and his father before him.
我的妻子，是在这里出生的，在艾文泰
My wife- my wife was born here in the Aventine!
我和这里的所有其它人一样，是一个罗马人
I am as solid a Roman as any man here!
如果我被选为你们的地区长官
If I am elected as your local magistrate,
我以朱庇特石的名义起誓
I promise on Jupiter's stone
努力创造出一个和平
to strive to make this an era of peace,
繁荣，公正的时期
prosperity and justice
为所有的艾文泰居民
for all Aventine.
明天
Tomorrow
恺撒将会举办一个凯旋庆典
Caesar holds a triumph,
作为他对于罗马人民爱的见证
a symbol of his love for the people of Rome.
笑话！
Cac!  Why don't you shut up, you--
你为什么不闭上你的嘴，你…
保持风度，夫人，保持风度
Ladylike, madam, ladylike.
五天的盛会和娱乐
Five days of feasting and games
是对罗马人民给予
as appreciation for the trust and support
恺撒的理解和支持的回报
the people of Rome have given Caesar.
自由，准确的说，我们把自由都给了他
Freedom, more like! We've given him our freedom
还有尊严
and our honor!
如果我不相信和了解恺撒
I would not be standing here on Caesar's slate
才是这个国家的救星
if I did not believe, if I did not know
我也就不会站在这里为他说话了
that he has only the Republic's best interests at heart.
“一个新的时代”
"A new era."
“明天的凯旋庆典，是一个新的时代的开始”
"Tomorrow's triumph, a new era."
明天的凯旋庆典，是一个新的时代的开始
With tomorrow's triumph, a new era begins.
对于所有艾文泰的人以及所有的罗马人
For all Aventine. For all Rome.
很好，你做的很不错  谢谢
It was good. You did well.  Thank you.
高卢人的王
King of all the Gauls.
让你有些想法，不是吗？
Makes you think, doesn't it?
确实如此
It does.
再见了，老朋友
Goodbye, old friend.
尽量把他收拾的干净些，他看上去已经是个死人了
Do your best to tidy him up. He looks dead already.
总算找到你们了，混蛋
Found you at last, you bastards.
我找遍了整个军队  赫赫有名的泰特斯·波罗
I've been through the whole damned army. The famous Titus Pullo.
是什么让我们有这种荣幸呢，公民？
To what do we owe this honor, citizen?
是来祝福我们好运的吗？
Do you come to wish us luck?
听着，我大部分的装备都还在，就是头盔找不到了
Listen, I've got most of my kit, but I've lost my crest.
肯定有人有多余的吧，你们说那？
Surely someone's got a spare, you think?
只是个头盔罢了，又不是失去了剑
It's only a crest. It's not like I lost my sword.
你不能跟参与我们的阅兵式
Well, you can't march with us.
你已经离开了军团，你自己要离开的
You've left the Legion. You signed yourself out.
我知道，但是永远是13军的人，不是吗？
I know, but... 13th forever, eh?
只有军人可以参加凯旋庆典，你只是个公民
It's enlisted men only in the triumph. You're a civilian.
公民？
Civilian?
我是军团的英雄
I'm the hero of the whole mumping Legion, I am.
我不止一次的救了你
I saved your skin more than once. Shouldn't have to remind you of that.
我想这不用我来提醒你
如果你想要再当几年兵的话，那就另当别论
If you want to sign up for a few more years,
你可以加入阅兵式，直到你走到脚肿
that's a different story. You can march with us till your feet are nubs.
我为13军流的血难道还不够吗？
Haven't I spilled enough blood for the 13th?
别那样
Don't be like that.
不是我他妈定的规矩，对吗
I don't fucking make the rules, do l? I follow them.
我只是执行罢了
It's enlisted men only. Don't push it.
只有军人可以参加，别推到我头上来
如果宴会结束之后你想过来，我可以请你点喝的，嗯？
If you come by after, I'll stand you some drinks, eh?
请我喝点？
Stand me some drinks?
我可不想和你这样的人一起喝什么酒
I've got better things to do than go drinking
好啊，走吧，公民
with the likes of you.  Well, walk on then, citizen.
走！
Walk on!
好了，伙计们，精神点
Right, ladies, on your feet!
是时候拿出点军人的样子来了！
Time to look like soldiers!
这会不会太繁琐了一些？
Is this too much?
在我看来，正好  我不这么看…
Just enough, I'd say.  I don't know.
我认为这紫色太刺眼了，我想让人感到紫色（王权）
I think it's too purple. I want to suggest purple
但不想穿着紫色
without actually wearing it.
在光线照射下，不会看上去太刺眼
It will look less loud in direct light.
你怎么看？ 朱庇特再世
What do you think?  Jupiter in life.
毫无二致
Resemblance is uncanny.
有什么东西让你感到好笑吗？
What do you find amusing?
很荒缪，不是吗？
It's absurd, isn't it?
盛装打扮，扮演成神的样子
Dressing up, playing at being God?
扮演？
Playing?
我可不是在扮演
I'm not playing.
这可不是什么游戏
This is not a game.
如你所想
As you wish.
这不是游戏
It is not a game.
来点红色的
Something more red.
斗技场周围的水沟都灌满了吗？ 是的
Is the canal around the circus filled?  It is.
昨天晚上还没好呢
It was not last night.
今天早上就已经好了  很好
I saw to it at first light.  very good.
要保证大象们在合适的时候吃药
Make sure the elephants are given their emetics in good time.
我可不想因为这些巨大的蠢东西让我的战车放慢脚步
I don't want my chariot slowed by giant turds.
你看起来好多了
You are looking much better.
我自己倒没那个感觉
I am not better, however.
也许我必须送你到乡下去
Well, I must get you out to the country, perhaps.
一点…
Some fresh air and sunshine would do you good.
新鲜的空气和阳光对你有好处
总在床上躺着可不是办法
This lying abed is not healthy.
有事情做的时候我才起床
I rise when I have reason to do so.
别在这虚情假意了
Don't loiter here pretending to be solicitous.
到你朋友那种污秽的聚会上去吧
Go to your friend's obscene display.
母亲…
Mother...
走！
Go.
脸颊上需要再上点颜色吗？
Do you want some color on your cheeks?
求你了，亲爱的
Please, darling,
说话吧
say something.
这种可怕的沉默
This horrid silent business,
真是让人不安
it's most upsetting.
他们对你做了点什么？ 他们什么都没做
What did they do to you?  They did nothing.
她终于说话了，这是个好的开始
She speaks. There's a start.
他们对我很好
They were very kind to me.
好到让你像对待猪肋肉一样
Kind enough to let you hack away at yourself
伤害自己
Iike a side of pork.
我可怜的小脾气鬼
My poor little grump.
我直到现在才发现我是多么的想念
Oh, I didn't realize until now how much I missed
你着这里忧郁的存在
your gloomy presence around the place.
女主人…
Domina...
有个乞丐在门口，自称是昆特斯
there's a beggar at the door who says he is Quintus,
庞贝的儿子
natural son of Pompey.
来寻求您儿子的保护
He asks for your son's protection.
把他赶走
Send him away.
放开！ 滚出去！
Take your hands off me!  Get out!
布鲁图斯
Brutus!
不敢跟我见面吗？懦夫？
Scared to talk to me, eh, coward?
你是个懦夫，布鲁图斯
You're a coward, Brutus!
我以门神的名义起誓
I swear by Janus,
朱庇特还有朱诺（朱庇特之妻）
Jupiter and Juno,
我在我父亲的墓碑前发誓
I swear on the grave of my father,
我，昆特斯·维拉里斯·庞贝
I, Quintus valerius Pompey,
我要杀了那个暴君
I'm going to kill that son of a whore tyrant!
我让阿贾克斯去打发他走
I'll get Ajax to deal with him
他是罗马的叛国贼  等等
He's a bastard traitor to Rome...  Wait.
你也是叛徒，布鲁图斯
and you're a traitor too, Brutus!
庞贝的儿子，对吗？
Pompey's natural son, eh?
我就是
I am.
我想你肯定不是恺撒的朋友
I gather at least you're still no friend to Caesar.
我要把他活活烧死
I'll burn him alive.
我要把他的眼睛挖出来
I will pluck out his eyes, l-  Shh shh.
冷静些
Be calm.
这里的人都是你的朋友
You're among friends.
一切都会好起来的
Allwill bewell.
带他沐浴，给他弄点吃的
Have him washed and fed.
恺撒！恺撒！
Caesar! Caesar!
伟大的恺撒！
Glorious Caesar!
神眷顾你，恺撒！
The gods favor you, Caesar!
恺撒！恺撒！
Caesar! Caesar!
能够容纳5000个人的桌子
"Tables for 5000 men
会放在广场上
will be set up in the cattle forum.
奴隶和自由身的人没有资格加入
Slaves and freedmen are not eligible.
那些没有位子坐的平民必须在
Those citizens that cannot find a proper seating place must leave
市政长官要求的时候离开
when ordered by the civic officers.
盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒已宣布
Gaius Julius Caesar has decreed
为了感谢大家的崇高美德
in tribute to their virtue,
每一个罗马的臣民
each and every citizen of Rome
都将从国库得到
will be issued from the public treasury
100便士
the sum of 100 denarii."
除此之外
"Further,
20,000户应受奖励的家庭
20,000 deserving families
将得到在卡普阿
will be given farms
附近的农田
on the public lands around Capua."
除此之外，来年
"Further, for the coming year,
所有的租金
all rents- all rents
城里底层人们的所有的租金
on low dwellings in the city
都将由
will be paid in full
盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒支付
by Gaius Julius Caesar."
高贵极了
very noble
我想这实在是太完美的表述了
and very nicely expressed, if I may say so.
我们能私下聊聊吗？
Might I have a quiet word?
当然
Of course.
私下聊
A quiet word.
你可以当着昆特斯的面说
Oh, you may speak in front of Quintus.
好吧，我要说的就是昆特斯
As you wish. It is of Quintus I speak.
这家伙来这也有几天了吧
The good man has been here several days now.
也是时候可以走人了吧
Perhaps he grows weary of entertaining us with his happy presence.
别介意，昆特斯，他就是这么缺乏礼貌
Do not mind him, Quintus. He has no manners.
只要他还能让我高兴，他就可以住在这里
He shall stay as long as it pleases me.
问题就在这里，母亲
Well, that's the thing, Mother.
我没有发现他有任何
I do not see in what way he could
可以让您高兴的地方
possibly please you.
他的目的是什么？
What is his purpose?
他能说明您写诗吗？
Does he help you to write poetry?
他是一个好的聆听者  是吗？
He has a good ear.  lndeed? Hmm.
真让我意外  他有着火热的内心
You surprise me.  He has fire in him.
让我感到温暖
It warms me.
如果觉得冷就多点灯
Light more lamps if you are cold!
让庞贝的儿子呆在我们家里很不舒服
It looks very ill to keep a son of Pompey in our house.
我们应该以此为傲！
And we should strike such fine figures otherwise!
你瞧
So you see, the fourth clause
这上级法令的第四个条款
of the previous statute only applies in cases of fire and flood,
只在火灾和洪水时候
或者是符合附录中的规定的时候才适用
unless otherwise stipulated in the appendix.
明白了吗？ 不是很清楚
Do you see?  Not clearly.
我没有办法解释的更简单了
I'm not sure I can explain it in simpler terms.
这些可以等选举结束后再讨论
Surely this can wait until after the election.
如果我输了，学这些有什么用？
There's no point learning all this if I lose.
你不会输的
You will not lose.
为什么你这么肯定？还有其它候选人
You're very sure of that. There are other candidates.
我想我警告过你嘲笑我是什么后果
I believe I warned you about mocking me.
请原谅，先生，但我以为你已经了解了这个制度
Forgive me, sir. I had thought you understood the system.
其它候选人都只是凑数的
The other candidates are straw men.
凑数的？
Straw men?
但是如果没有反对者
It saves a great deal of useless strife
当然能够避免无意义的竞争，但只有恺撒的人
if there's no opposition, but it would look ill
站出来又会显得太突兀
if Caesar's man was the only one standing.
这些事实让你困扰吗？
These facts disturb you somehow?
选举是由神圣的朱庇特神监督的
The elections are sanctioned by Jupiter Capitolinus.
选举可是庄严的事情啊
They are sacred.
恺撒也是由朱庇特神指派的，不是吗？
Caesar also is sanctioned by Jupiter, is he not?
有预兆，有胜利的凯旋
By augury, by triumph,
也有人民的拥护
by acclaim of the people.
他所作的一切，都是由神庇护的
Anything he does is sacred.
某种程度上，他就是神本身
In a way, he is a demigod.
仅仅在那一天而已
For one day only.
其它日子里，他和你我一样，都是凡人
For the rest, he is a mortal man like you and me.
不管他是不是凡人，他在试图拯救共和国
Mortal or not, he is trying to save the Republic.
通过贿赂选举？
By corrupting the elections?
罗马人民可没有期盼干净的选举
The Roman people are not crying out for clean elections.
他们期盼的是工作
They are crying out for jobs.
他们期盼的是甘甜的水和食物
They are crying out for clean water, for food,
和平稳定的生活
for stability and peace.
你可以为人们做到这些
You can do great things for your people.
你可以帮助恺撒
You can help
拯救共和国
save the Republic.
或者你可以回到你的小店铺去继续卖你的羊肉跟猪肉
Or you can go back to your shop and resume selling mutton and pig,
满手污泥却保持一颗高尚的心
have dirty hands but a clean conscience.
你怎么想？
So what do you say?
什么？
Say to what?
你根本没在听我说什么
You haven't heard a word I've been saying.
没事吧？
Is everything all right?
原谅我
Forgive me.
那…你需要什么？
So what was it you needed?
我想让艾瑞纳脱离奴籍，带她去乡下过日子
I want to free Eirene, take her off to the country,
如果你能借我点钱  当然可以
if you'll lend me some money.  Of course.
我还想让你陪我一起去奴役登记处
And I'll need you to come with me to the slave registry,
用你的名字做我的担保人
to vouch your name for my ownership.  Slow down. Why are you freeing Eirene?
等一下，你为什么要让艾瑞纳脱离奴籍？
如果她是奴隶我就不能娶她
Can't marry her otherwise.  Marry her?
娶她？
听着…我…
Look, I've--
我最近…很消沉…
I've been feeling strange and low
这几个月来一直是这个样子
and empty these last months, and...
不管怎么样，我现在是想通了，我明白我为什么会这样了
anyway, I've puzzled it out, and I realized what it was.
我爱艾瑞纳
I love Eirene.
我爱她，我想和她一起拥有我们的孩子
I love her, and I want her to bear my children
让她做我的妻子…
and be my wife, and...
我想我只能说恭喜了…
Congratulations, I suppose.
那么…你说你要去乡下？
So you'll be going to the country, you say?
要离开罗马？
Leaving Rome?
罗马不是我应该呆的地方
Rome's no place for me.
我需要新鲜的空气，自由的空间
I need clean air, room to move.
那么你到了乡下打算靠什么谋生？
And what will you do when you get there?
一个强壮的男人到哪都能有口饭吃
There's always work for a good man with a sword.
好吧，既然你已经打定主意了…
Well, as long as you're sure.
我都考虑清楚了
Oh, I've thought it through.
我这辈子从来没有这么肯定过
I've never been so sure of anything in my life.
我为你高兴
I'm happy for you.
希望你找到自己生活的路
I hope you find your path.
怎么还呆在这里？
Still here? I thought you were
我还以为你已经为了你的尊严隐居乡下了呢
retiring to the country as a point of honor.
你尽可以嘲笑我
You do right to mock me.
你让我感到渺小
You make me feel small.
开个玩笑，老人家，只是个玩笑
A joke, old man, a joke. I'm always happy for your company.
有你在我总是感到快乐
那么…你为什么不事先告诉我
So, why didn't you tell me beforehand?
我至少可以给你提供一点帮助
I could have been of assistance perhaps.
你在说什么？
What are you talking about?
所有人都在看这个
Everyone is reading it!
我从神殿里的女奴那拿到的抄本
I saw some temple prostitutes with a copy.
“觉醒吧！道德”
"A call to virtue."
文章本身是没有什么问题
The writing is... adequate, which is something
只是有些地方我们得讨论一下，但是观点却是十分
we should talk about, but the sentiments are
高贵和勇敢的
full of grace and bravery.
共和国的子民，先辈的血液
"Sons of the Republic, the blood of our forefathers
呼唤着你们不要遗忘过去，行动起来…
calls you to honor the memory and emulate the deeds
波卡斯·卡托，最后一个真正的罗马人
of Porcius Cato, the last true Roman."
谁写的这个？
Who wrote this?
你写的
You did.
神灵保佑我们！
Gods beneath us!
母亲！！
Mother!
母亲…你读过这个了吗？
Mother, have you seen this?
这篇疯狂的东西？
This lunacy?
我当然看过了
Of course I've seen it.
这不是什么疯狂
It's not lunacy.
这是在暴政的统治下
It is a cogent defense of Republican principles
对共和国原则的扞卫
against the forces of tyranny.
我为此感到骄傲
I am rather proud of it.
是你写的？
You wrote this?
用我的名义？
In my name?
卡西亚斯
Cassius contributed
给文章修饰了一下
several nice turns of phrase.
你肯定认得卡西亚斯
You know Cassius, of course.
很高兴见到你，当然
Of course. Delighted.
昆特斯
Quintus.
很高兴再次见到你
It's lovely to see you again.
好久不见了  是啊…
It's been too long.  lndeed.
请原谅…
You will excuse me
我想和我妈妈私下谈谈
if I speak with my mother privately?
我很抱歉让你失望了…
I'm deeply sorry you feel I have failed you,
但是这也做的太过分了
but this- this is going too far.
你不能就这样用我的名义…
My name is not yours to be used--
你没有让我失望
You haven't failed me.
你永远不会让我失望，因为我是你的母亲
You can't fail me, I'm your mother.
你只是让共和国失望了  我的老天啊！
You have failed the Republic.  Dear gods!
把笔和纸给我拿来
Bring me a pen and paper. It's bad enough
让那个疯子腔昆特斯
留在这里已经够糟糕的了
that you keep that little madman Quintus in this house,
但是这个！
but this- this!
我不知道我该如何向他解释  你为什么不跪下来
I don't know what to tell him.  Why don't you
亲吻他的脚，请求他的宽恕？
fall on your knees and kiss his feet and beg for mercy?
你过去曾经这样成功过  但你呢？
It served you in the past.  But not you.
也许你恳求的不够中肯
Eh? Perhaps you did not beg hard enough.
你…
You...
你明白吗…
you do understand...
他也许会为了这个而杀了我？
he might have me killed for this?
罗马已经沦落到了一个恶魔的手里
Rome has fallen into the hands of a corrupt monster.
你
You, direct descendant
作为共和国建立者
的直系后代
of the father of the Republic,
应该做点什么
what do you do?
你想让我怎么做？
What would you have me do?
想想你父亲会怎么做吧？
What would your father have done?
你的祖父会怎么做？
What would his father have done? Would they bend their knees
他们会向一个暴君下跪吗？
to a tyrant?  They would take account
他们至少会
of the specific circumstan--
审时度势…
他们会象疯狗一样赶走这个暴君！
They would chase him out of the city like any mad dog.
赶走他？
Chased him out?
那么我应该如何做呢？
And how am l to do that exactly?
你不是孤单一人
You would not be alone.
啊，对，这个屋子里的这些人
Ah, these fine men in the house
都非常优秀，这点我相信
are very very good. I am reassured.
他们是很棒，还有其它许多人也很棒
They are good men. And there are many others,
有头脑，有智慧的那些人
men of rank and wisdom.
那可不是什么疯狗
It is not a dog gone mad.
我宁愿疯狂也不愿玷污我们的名声
I would rather be mad than disgrace our name.
别说了
No more!
把你的那些追随者赶走
You send your fool henchmen away...
忘了这件愚蠢的事情
and forget this insanity.
布鲁图斯  卡西亚斯，再见到你真的很高兴
Brutus.  Ah, Cassius, it's lovely to see you,
但是…如你所见…
but, as you can see--
当然，请原谅我们擅自拜访
Of course, forgive the intrusion.
也许我们应该改天拜访
Perhaps I may visit another time.
很好，当然
Good. Certainly.
在朱庇特石的名义下，你是一个罗马公民
On Jupiter's stone, you're a full Roman citizen,
你愿意为这个男人列出这些他拥有的财产做担保吗？
and you attest to this man's ownership of listed property?
当然，我愿意
I am. I do.
在这里签字
Sign here.
任何记号都可以了
Any kind of mark will do.
我会写我自己的名字！
I can write my name as good as the next man.
好了
Done.
42,42号过来
42. 42 up.
艾瑞纳
Eirene.
过来，我想和你谈谈
Come over here. I want to talk to you.
我让你们单独聊聊
I'll leave you to it.
我刚去了奴隶登记处，你已经不在是我的奴隶了
I've been to the registrar of slaves. You're no longer my slave.
你把我卖了？
You've sold me? Oh, please don't sell me.
请别把我卖掉
别把我送走，我求你了
Don't send me away. I beg you.
我让你自由了
I'm setting you free.
你自由了，你可以看看这里
You're free. It says so here.
谢谢
Thank you.
太谢谢你了，你是这个世界上最好的人
Thank you. You're the kindest man alive.
我爱你，先生 我爱你，先生
I love you, sir. I love you, sir.
这里有件衣服
Here. Here. It's a dress.
拿去试试吧
Um, go try it on.
让我们看看合不合适
Let's see how it looks.
泰特斯·波罗先生我简直不知道应该如何感谢你
Titus Pullo, sir. I cannot thank you enough.
谢我？为什么？
Thank me? What are you thanking me for, boy?
你让她自由了
For freeing her. We have been saving to buy our freedom,
我们一直在存钱打算为自己赎身
但我们没想过一切来的是那么快
but we never- to happen so soon.
这简直是上天赐给我们的礼物
I cannot tell you what a gift it is.
你们一起存钱？你和艾瑞纳？
You've both been saving? You and Eirene?
我们想过要用乌瑞纳斯
We thought to take the vorenus name as ours
作为我们自由后的姓氏
when we became freedmen,
但是艾瑞纳说必须以你的名义
but Eirene says it must be under your name
她才做我的妻子
she becomes my wife.
妻子？
Wife?
我是说，法定的妻子
Legal wife, I mean.
我们早就在心中结为夫妻了
We are already married in our hearts.
艾瑞纳？我的艾瑞纳？
Eirene? My Eirene?
先生？
Sir?
Sir!
死了？
Dead?  Looks like.
看起来是…
What happened?  I killed him. I did it.
怎么了？
我杀了他，是我干的
我知道，但是为什么，为什么要这么做？
I can see that, but why? Why did you do this?
没所谓了
It doesn't matter.  It does matter, though.
怎么会无所谓
It matters to me. This boy was my property.
这关系到我
这家伙是我的财产
他激怒了我  他激怒了你？
He angered me.  He angered you?
他…他和艾瑞纳，他们是…
He- he and Eirene, they were--
那又有关系？难道你以为她是处女吗？
So what does that matter? Did you think she was a virgin?
她依然是你的，你可以拥有她
She's still yours to use as you wish.
我爱她
I love her.
你这就是爱的证明？
This is how you prove it?
这可不是停尸房，随便让你杀人的地方
This is no charnel house to kill people as you want.
这是我的房子，我的家！
This is my home. My home!
Shh.
你在我的孩子面前干出这样的事情？！
You do this violence before my children?!
对不起…
I'm sorry.
我会赔偿你的
I'll pay you back.
你用什么来赔偿，你这个傻瓜
Pay me back with what, you damn fool?
除了我给你的钱，你一无所有
You've got no money but what I've given you.
但是请你…
But please...
别叫我傻瓜
do not call me a fool.
我就是要这么叫你，你这个傻瓜
I'll call you what I like. You're a damn fool.
我不在乎钱…
I don't care about the money.
但你这么做太失礼了
It's the disrespect.
看看你都干了些什么，看看他！
Look at what you did! Look at him!
也许你是对的
Maybe you're right.
也许我是个傻瓜
Probably am a fool.
永远都没有办法像你那么聪明
Never was a clever one like you.
从来没有降过职，从来没有受过处罚，从来没有被关过禁闭
Never demoted, you, never flogged, never locked up.
一直在往上爬
Straight to the top.
看看现在的你
And here you are,
穿着干净，漂亮的官袍
with your nice, clean, white toga.
不管你内在是多么的肮脏
Lovely cloth, that.
外表始终是那么的光鲜亮丽
Stays clean no matter how much you wade in the filth.
想说什么就直说
Speak your mind.  As you will.
好吧，你曾经说过恺撒是个叛徒
Time was, you said Caesar was a rebel and a traitor.
他给了你钱和土地，但是现在呢？
And now, today, he tosses you some coin and some farmland,
他变成了共和国的救世主
and he's savior of the Republic, and you're kissing his royal ass.
你在他面前极尽阿谀奉承之能事
你给我站起来！
You stand up.
站起来！站起来！
Stand up! Stand up!
我不想和你打
I'll not fight you.
那就滚！
Then go.
离开这里，永远别回来！
Go and do not come back here.
走，走，别回到这里来！
Go. Go! And do not come back here.
艾瑞纳，我很抱歉，我很抱歉…
Eirene, I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
离她远点…
Stay away from her.
好吧
Right.
对不起…
Sorry.
我完全不知情
I had no idea.
我要走了
I must go now.
你…
You- you do believe me?
你相信我？
我亲爱的朋友，我当然相信你
My dear friend, of course I believe you.
你从来不会对我撒谎
You have never lied to me.
除此之外，为什么你要把你的名字签上去
Besides, why would you put your name to a thing
然后又否认呢？ 是的，正是如此
and then deny it?  Well, exactly.
但是任何人都可以利用我的名字
And anyone- anyone may forge my name to a thing
来使某些东西招人耳目
to give it weight.
我想我们必须开始习惯
We shall just have to become used to it, no doubt.
我很想知道是谁写的
I wonder who it was that wrote it.
我也是
I wish I knew.
一定是个有天赋的人 我还真是很少见到
Someone of talent. Anyhow, I've seldom seen
能够把一件坏事表述得如此好的人呢
a bad case so well put.
也许我该回击他
I shall have to write a reply.
其实，只要你跟我能够明白我们的立场
Well, as long as you and I know where we stand.
我们的立场？
Where do we stand?
我希望我们还是最好的朋友？
I hope we are the best of friends. Are we?
当然，我们当然是
We are, we are.
布鲁图斯，我从来没有质疑过你的友谊和忠诚
Brutus, I have never doubted your friendship or fidelity.
即便是我们互相对立的时候
Even when we were enemies.
泰特斯·波罗
Titus Pullo.
你看起来疲惫极了
You look tired, my friend.
我喝醉了
I'm drunk.  These are hard times for war veterans.
现在，战场上的老兵不吃香了
你说得对
You're right there.
太多的士兵回到罗马
Too many soldiers back in Rome.
却没有那么多的工作，世道真是不行了
Not enough work to go round. It's a sad situation.
有你这样的好身手
But it's a crime
却流离失所，简直是罪过
to see a man of your ability unemployed.
我很好
I'm doing fine.
我有一身的本领
I have plenty of irons in the fire.
如果你的抱负没有办法实现
Well, if your prospects don't work out,
你可以去艾文泰大街上找一下
you can ask on any street in the Aventine
易拉斯泰斯·福曼
for Erastes Fulman.
我这有适合你的工作
I will always have a job for you.
我是个士兵，不是杀手
I'm a soldier, not a murderer.
在这个时代，这两种人，有区别么？
These days, Pullo, is there really any difference?
这杯算我的
Have a drink on me.
等你清醒了以后，可以来找我
When you've sobered up, come and see me.
我们可以谈点生意
We'll talk a little business.
翻译:TLF字幕组